听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
大家好 欢迎来到分布式系统的第4课
Hello everyone. Welcome to lecture 4 of distributed systems.
今天 我们将讨论广播协议和逻辑时间
Today, we will be talking about broadcast protocols and logical time.
作为背景知识 回忆一下上一节课的这页幻灯片
As background, remember this slide here from the last lecture,
我们有两条消息
where we have the case of two messages.
第一条消息是用户A说“月亮是奶酪做的！”
First, m_1 is user A says “The moon is made of cheese!”,
第二条消息是用户B回复m_1的m_2：“不 不是的！”
m_2 is user B replies to m_1 saying “Oh, no, it isn't!”.
使用物理时钟所面临的问题是
And what could happen with physical clocks is that
m_1的时间戳可能会比m_2的时间戳大
the timestamp of m_1 ends up being greater than the timestamp of m_2.
有可能出现的一种情况是 两个时间戳的大小关系
So, it could be the case that those timestamps are inconsistent with the order
与我们期望的事件发生顺序不一致
that we intuitively expect of those two messages,
两个消息的时间戳大小关系与事件的因果关系不一致
that those messages are inconsistent with causality.
即使我们使用NTP协议等各种方法同步时钟
Now, this is a problem with physical clocks
使用物理时钟仍然可能会遇到上述问题
even after we've gone to all of these efforts to synchronize them using NTP.
即便进行了时钟同步 时间戳大小关系与事件的因果关系也可能不一致
Even then, it could happen that you get these inconsistencies with causality.
这时就要引入逻辑时钟了
So, this is where logical clocks come in.
逻辑时钟是分布式系统对时钟的另一种定义
Logical clocks are an alternative definition of clocks that are used in distributed systems,
设计逻辑时钟就是为了描述
which are specifically designed to capture the causal relationships
系统中所发生事件的因果关系
between the events that happen in a system.
逻辑时钟也是一种时钟
And so, logical clocks, they are sort of clocks.
逻辑时钟并不是传统意义上的时钟
They're not clocks in the sense of
不用来度量时间
measuring how long it's been,
不用来度量地球围绕太阳的公转周期
measuring how far the earth has turned around the sun,
不用来度量地球的自转周期
measuring how far the earth has rotated around its own axis, those kinds of things.
那些都是物理时间
That's all physical time.
在逻辑时间中 我们对时间流逝了多少秒不感兴趣
In logical time, we're not actually interested in how many seconds have elapsed.
我们感兴趣的是发生了多少个事件
Instead, what we're interested in is how many events have occurred.
逻辑时间戳本质上只是一个计数器
And so, logical timestamps are essentially just counters that we increment
只要发生了某件事 就增加计数器的计数值
every time when something happens.
这意味着逻辑时间也随时间流逝而增加
And so, this means they do move forwards in time. They get greater as stuff happens.
但逻辑时间和物理时间没有直接关系
But they don't have a direct relationship to physical time.
我们希望逻辑时间完成的工作是
So, the key thing that we want of a logical clock is that
表达因果关系 表达此前发生关系
it captures causality, it captures the happens-before relationship.
特别地 如果e_1→e_2
In particular, if e_1→e_2,
则我们希望e_1的时间戳小于e_2的时间戳
then we want the timestamp of e_1 to be less than the timestamp of e_2.
这是我们期望逻辑时钟所满足的最小要求
This is like a minimum basic thing that we expect of our logical clocks.
我们将学习逻辑时钟的两种构造方法
And we're going to look at two different constructions of logical clocks,
Lamport时钟和向量时钟
Lamport clocks and vector clocks.
这两种逻辑时钟都可以表达因果关系
Both of these satisfy this need to capture causality,
但它们有一些微小的不同点 适合在不同场景下使用 我们稍后就会讲到
but they have slightly different properties in other areas as we shall see.
我们先从Lamport时钟开始
So, let's start with Lamport clocks.
此时钟因Leslie Lamport而命名
These are named after Leslie Lamport,
他在1978年左右发表了此时钟算法的论文
who published this algorithm in about 1978 or so.
这是分布式系统非常经典的算法
And this has really been a classic of distributed systems.
此算法非常简单
And the algorithm is fairly simple.
算法启动时 每个节点都有一个变量t
So, the algorithm starts at every node we have a variable that we call t.
当启动系统时 此变量被初始化为0
And this variable is initialized to 0 when we start up the system.
每个节点分别持有自己的变量 每个节点都拥有自己的t
And each node has its own copy of this variable. Each node has its own t.
当节点中发生某个事件时 我们增加t
And every time when some event occurs at a node, we just increment t.
事件可以是节点在本地执行了一个步骤
So, an event could be some local execution step taking place.
事件也可以是节点发送或接收了一条消息
So, it could be sending a message or receiving a message.
只要发生了一个事件 我们就增加t
In all of these cases, we just increment t.
现在 每当我们想通过网络发送一条消息或者想执行本地事件
Now, every time we want to send a message over the network,
我们就增加t
we increment t as usual as for any local event.
增加t后 我们取t的值
And also, we take the value of t after incrementing it.
将t的值附加在消息上
And we attach that to the message.
我们发送的消息是时间戳和实际消息所组成的数据对
So, the message we send is actually this pair of a timestamp and the actual message.
这就是我们要通过网络发送的消息
And that is what gets sent on the network.
现在 当另一端收到了其中一个数据对后
Now, when one of these pairs is received at the other end,
收到消息的节点从数据对中取出时间戳
the node that is receiving the message takes the timestamp out of the message,
t'表示从消息中取出的时间戳
t' is the timestamp in the message.
同时 节点查看自己的本地变量t
And it looks at its own local variable t.
他将t更新为
And it updates t to be the maximum of
本地时间戳和消息时间戳的最大值再加1
either its own local existing timestamp or the timestamp of the message, plus 1,
就像本地执行事件那样增加t
incrementing it again like for every local event.
完成这一步后 我们就得到了更新后的t
And so, after this has been done, we've got updated value t.
我们将消息传递给应用程序
And we deliver the message to the application.
我们再来仔细研究一下Lamport时钟
So, let's look at a bit of around Lamport clocks.
每个节点都有一个计数器t
So, we have this counter t here on each node.
每个事件都可以与t的一个特定取值相关联
And we can associate a particular value of t with every event.
我们把一个本地发生的事件称为事件e
So, let's say that some local event occurred and called that event e.
对于每一个本地事件 我们都增加计数器的值
For every local event, we increment the counter.
增加完毕后
So, after that increment,
我们取出计数器的值 将其与事件e相关联
we take the value of that counter and associated that with that event e,
关联结果为L(e) 表示这是一个Lamport时钟
and call that L(e) for Lamport clock.
我前面讲到
As I said,
我们把此计数器值也附加在消息上 通过网络一起发送出去
we attach those values over on the messages that we send over the network as well.
Lamport时钟拥有非常好的性质
And so, these Lamport clocks have some very nice properties.
首先 如果a→b 则这个方案将保证
First of all, if a→b, then this scheme guarantees that
事件a的Lamport时间戳
the Lamport timestamp of event a
将严格小于事件b的Lamport时间戳
is strictly less than the Lamport timestamp of event b.
讲义上的一个练习就是要让大家证明
And there's actually an exercise in the lecture notes that asks you to prove that
确实满足这个性质
this is indeed the case.
然而 逆命题不成立
However, the converse is not true.
如果我们对比两个Lamport时间戳
So, if we have two Lamport timestamps, and we compare them,
L(a)<L(b)并不意味着a→b
and we find that L(a)<L(b), that does not imply that a→b.
还可能出现的一种情况是a‖b
It could also be the case that a‖b.
也就是说 Lamport时间戳无法告诉我们到底是a‖b还是a→b
So, the Lamport timestamps don't allow us to tell whether a‖b or if a→b.
我们唯一可以确定的是可以排除b→a
The only thing we can do is we can rule out that b→a,
因为如果b→a 则时间戳大小关系应该反过来
because if b→a, then the timestamps would have to be the other way around.
Lamport时间戳可能出现的另一个现象是
Another thing that can happen with these Lamport timestamps is
两个不同的事件可能拥有相同的时间戳
it's possible that we have two different events with the same timestamp.
无法阻止这种情况的出现
There's nothing preventing this.
我们来看一个具体的例子
So, let's have a look at a concrete example here.
这里我们通过一些事件执行了一个任务
So, here we've got an execution with some events.
事件仍然用小黑点表示 网络仍然会传输一些发送的消息
The events are again little black blobs, and we have messages sent over the network.
节点A的第一个事件是本地事件 我们增加本地计数器的值
So, here for the first event by node A, we just increment the counter for that local event.
节点A的第二个事件是要通过网络发送消息m_1
The second event by node A is that we send the message m_1 over the network.
我们让时间戳2关联到此事件上
And so, here we have the timestamp 2 associated with that event.
我们还将此时间戳拷贝到要发送的消息中
And we also copied that timestamp into the message that we send,
将时间戳附加在消息上
and attach it to the message.
当B收到m_1之前 B的本地时间戳为0
Now here, when B receives m_1, before that, the local timestamp at B will just be 0,
因为B在收到消息之前没有任何事件
because no events have happened so far at B.
但当带有时间戳2的消息到达B后
But when the message with timestamp 2 arrives at B,
我们将B的本地时间戳前移 再加上1
we move the local timestamp forward to B, and increment it by 1 again.
这样 接收事件的时间戳就变成了3
So, we end up with 3 as this timestamp of the receive event.
B在本地发生了下一个事件 此事件关联的时间戳变成了4
Then, next local event happens at B, and that gets the timestamp of 4.
时间戳4会附加在消息m_2中 并通过网络发送出去
That timestamp 4 gets attached to the message m_2 that's sent over the network.
节点C也一样
And so, here, likewise, at node C, again,
C的本地时间戳前移为4+1 也就是5
the local timestamp at C gets moved forward to 4+1, which is 5.
请注意观察几个现象
Now, a few things to notice here.
第一个现象是 有两个不同的事件所对应的时间戳都是3
One is, for example, that there are two different events with the same timestamp 3,
有两个不同事件的时间戳都是1
and also, two different events with the timestamp 1.
我们还希望
And so, one thing we might want to do is to
在整个系统中 每个事件用唯一的一个时间戳所标识
have timestamps that uniquely identify events in the entire system.
具体实现方法是 将Lamport时间戳
And we can do this by combining the Lamport timestamp
与此事件发生的节点名称组合在一起
with the name of the node at which that particular event occurred.
举个例子 如果你查看A的事件
So, if we say here, for example, if you look at the events that happened at A,
在A的视角下 每个事件都包含一个唯一的时间戳
within the scope of A, each of the events has a unique timestamp,
因为我们总是会增加时间戳
because we always increment,
我们不会为同一节点的两个事件生成相同的时间戳
we never generate two events at the same node with the same timestamp.
因此 对于一个特定的节点来说 每个事件的时间戳都是唯一的
And so, therefore, within one particular node, each event timestamp is unique.
如果我们假定每个节点都有一个唯一的名字 如这里的A、B和C
So, if we assume that each node has a unique name, here like A, B and C,
我们将一个事件的Lamport时间戳
and we combine the Lamport timestamp of an event
和此事件发生的节点名称组合在一起
with the name of the node at which that event occurred,
这两个参数的组合将会唯一标识一个特定的事件
those two taken together will uniquely identify a particular event.
两者的组合就是一个唯一标识符
That combination is a unique identifier.
我们可以更新一下这个示意图
So, we could actually update this diagram here,
现在 每个事件上不仅标识了时间戳
and instead of just having the timestamp at each,
还标识了事件对应的节点名称
we have the pair of the timestamp and the node.
我们可以看到 这个事件的标识符为(3,A)
And now, we can see, here this event here has an identifier of (3,A),
这个事件的标识符为(3,B)
whereas this one here is (3,B).
不同事件的标识符不再相同
So, they're no longer the same.
Lamport时间戳还满足一个重要的性质
Now, there's one more thing that we can do with Lamport timestamps.
这个性质非常有用
And this is extremely useful.
我们可以应用此时间戳定义事件的全序关系
And that is we can define a total order using those.
假设我们有两个事件a和b
So, let's say we have two events a and b.
我们可以用弯曲小于号符号≺
And we can define that a is less than b
定义a小于b
according to this little curly less than symbol here,
a≺b当前仅当
a≺b if and only if
a的Lamport时间戳小于b的Lamport时间戳
the Lamport timestamp of a is less than the Lamport timestamp of b,
或者a和b拥有相同的Lamport时间戳
or if a and b have the same Lamport timestamp,
但事件a的节点名称小于事件b的节点名称
but the node name of event a is less than the node name of event b.
这意味着我们假设A、B和C等节点名称是可以相互比较的
So, this is assuming we have some way of comparing node names like A, B and C.
我们可以按照字母表顺序比较节点名称
We could just have like a lexicographic comparison of those
例如 A在B之前 B在C之间
so that A comes before B and B comes before C, for example.
这样一来 我们就可以定义事件的顺序了
And so, this now means we can define an ordering on these events
首先查看事件的Lamport时间戳
by first of all looking at their Lamport timestamps.
如果时间戳相同 我们用节点名称来打破相等性
and if the timestamps are the same, we break ties using the name of the nodes.
这一顺序定义方法称为全序关系
And this ordering here is a total order.
也就是说 对于任意两个事件 如果这两个事件不相同
That means for any two events, if they're distinct events,
则一定满足a≺b或b≺a
it is always the case that either a≺b or b≺a.
这不是偏序定义
So, it's not a partial order.
此前发生关系是偏序的
The happens-before relationship was a partial order,
换句话说 在此前发生关系下 我们无法比较并发事件的相互顺序
in which some events are incomparable if they are concurrent.
但这是全序关系定义
But here, this is a total order,
对于系统中任何位置发生的任何事件
which means any event that happened anywhere in the system,
我们都可以根据此种顺序定义为事件严格排序
we can always put them one after the other according to this order.
此顺序也与因果关系保持一致 也就是说 如果a→b
And this order is consistent with causality, which means that if a happens before b,
则根据全序关系 一定有a≺b
then it is always the case that that a≺b according to this total order.
可以直接从Lamport时间戳与因果关系保持一致
And that follows directly from the fact that
推导出此顺序也与因果关系保持一致
the Lamport timestamps are consistent with causality.
这就是Lamport时间戳
So, that's what Lamport timestamps are.
它是为系统中的事件附加时间戳的一种方法
They essentially give us a way of attaching timestamps to all of the events in a system
此方法可以表达此前发生关系
in a way that captures the happens-before relationships.
我们现在可以用事件的时间戳定义所有事件的全序关系了
So, we can now define this total order over the events using their timestamps.
我们利用时间戳
So, we can use the timestamps as a way of
标识系统中各个事件的发生顺序
detecting the order of the events that happened in the system.
在“月亮是由奶酪做的”的例子中
And in our example of “the moon being made of cheese”,
我们很确定
it would certainly be the case that
第一条消息的时间戳小于回复消息的时间戳
the first message would have a lower timestamp than the reply to that message.
这就是Lamport时间戳的定义 以及Lamport时钟所能带来的保证
This is what Lamport timestamps, Lamport clocks guarantee.
但Lamport时钟不是完美的 它还有一些局限性
But there are still limitations. The Lamport clocks are not perfect.
其中一个局限性是
One limitation is that
如果你有两个Lamport时间戳L(a)和L(b)
if you're given the two Lamport timestamps L(a) and L(b),
假定L(a)<L(b) 你无法得知到底是a→b还是a‖b
and let's say L(a)<L(b), you can't actually tell whether a→b or if a‖b.
我们可以说不满足b→a 因为如果是这样
We can tell that b did not happen before a, because if that were the case,
则Lamport时间戳的大小关系应该反过来
the Lamport timestamps would have to be the other way around.
我们可以得到一些信息
So, we can tell something,
但我们无法得知
but we can't actually tell the difference
两个事件是并发的
between two events that are concurrent
还是其中一个事件在另一个事件之前发生
and two events where one happened before the other.
如果一个逻辑时钟方案能告知我们这一点 那可能会带来很大的帮助
So, it might also be useful to have a scheme of logical clocks
我们希望逻辑时钟方案可以告诉我们
in which it is possible to tell the difference
两个事件是并发的
between two events that are concurrent
还是其中一个事件在另一个事件之前发生
and two events where one happened before the other.
这就是向量时钟的作用
And this is where vector clocks come in.
向量时钟是另一种逻辑时钟方案
So, vector clocks are a different scheme for logical time
此时钟可以区分并发和此前发生
that allows us to tell this difference.
向量时钟的工作原理如下
So, vector clocks work as follows.
首先 我们需要假设我们知道系统中所有节点的名称
First of all, we're going to assume we know the names of all of the nodes in the system.
假设系统中有n个节点
Let's say, we have n nodes in the system.
我们将这n个名称放在一个向量中
And we're just going to put them in a vector.
这是一个n维向量
So, this is an n-dimensional vector,
向量中的每一个元素代表了系统中的一个节点
where each of the elements of the vector is one of the nodes in the system.
我们把时间戳也定义为一个向量
And we can define timestamps which are also vectors.
向量时钟的时间戳由整数序列组成
So, in this case, we have a timestamp here consists of a sequence of integers.
系统中的每一个节点都对应向量中的一个整数
And we have one integer for every node in the system.
我们用尖括号来表示向量
Now, this is here written using these angle brackets as vector notation.
你可以把向量看成一个列表或一个整数数组
You could equally well think of this as a list or an array of integers.
现在 我们不用单个整数关联每一个事件了
And so, now, for every event, rather than associating a single number with it,
我们用整数向量关联每一个事件
we associate this vector of numbers with each event.
整数向量的含义是 向量的第i个元素 也就是这里的t_i
And the meaning of these numbers is that for the i-th entry in this vector, here t_i,
其含义是我们观察到节点N_i所发生的事件编号
that is the number of events that we have observed happening on node N_i.
我们按照Lamport时间戳的方法为事件计数
So, we're counting events like we did in the Lamport timestamps,
但现在 我们不把所有节点的计数结果混在一个计数器里
but now, rather than mixing all of the nodes together into a single counter,
我们为每一个节点的事件单独计数
we actually have a separate counter for every node
每一个特定的节点都有一个特定的事件计数器
for the number of events that have occurred on that particular node.
与Lamport时间戳类似
Now, like with the Lamport timestamps,
我们为每一个事件附加一个向量时间戳
we can attach a vector timestamp to every event.
我们需要按照一定的规则来更新时间戳
And there are certain rules for updating these timestamps.
当我们想计算一个特定事件的时间戳时
So, if we want to compute the timestamp for a particular event,
我们要做的第一件事是 每当节点N_i发生了一个事件
the first thing we do is every time that an event occurs at a node N_i,
我们根据节点在向量中的位置 增加向量中特定元素的计数器值
we increment the particular element of that vector corresponding to that particular node.
我们这里使用了方括号
So, I'm going to just use these square brackets here this notation
很多编程语言也用方括号来表示数组的下标
just like the array subscript in many programming languages.
方括号表示数组T所对应向量的第i个元素
It's just a way of referring to the i-th element of this vector or this array T here.
与Lamport时间戳类似
Like with the Lamport timestamps,
我们将向量时钟附加在消息上 并通过网络发送出去
we're going to attach vector clocks to messages that get sent over the network.
我们用一个算法来合并向量时间戳
And there's an algorithm for merging those.
我们现在介绍合并向量时间戳的算法
And we're going to look at this algorithm now.
合并算法的起始状态与Lamport时钟的合并算法类似
So here, we start in a way that is somewhat similar to the Lamport clocks.
每个节点本地都有一个时间戳
And that is, every node locally has a timestamp.
在向量算法中 时间戳不再是一个整数了
In this case, the timestamp is not just an integer,
而是一个初始值全为0的整数向量
but it's a vector of integers which starts off as being all 0.
系统中的每个节点都对应此向量的一个元素
So, we have one entry in this vector for each node in the system.
这是一个包含n个元素的向量
So, this is a vector that has n elements along here.
当系统中的节点发生了一个本地事件时
And every time a local event occurs somewhere in the system,
我们将根据发生事件所对应的节点
we're going to increment the particular vector element
增加向量中特定位置元素的计数器值
corresponding to the node at which that event occurs.
N_i处理了某个事件 则增加向量中自己位置的计数器值
So, N_i processes some event, it increments its own entry in the vector.
当我们想通过网络发送一条消息时
When we want to send a message over the network,
我们像发生本地事件一样 增加向量中自己位置的计数器值
again, we increment our own entry in the vector like for every local event.
随后 我们将向量T附加在消息上 通过网络发送出去
And then, we attach the vector T to the message to get sent of the network.
现在 当我们从网络中收到其中一条消息时
Now, when we receive one of these messages over the network,
令T'为消息中的时间戳
say, T' is the timestamp in the message,
我们现在要做的是
now we are going to
将接收方节点的本地时间戳T与消息中的时间戳T'合并到一起
merge the recipient nodes current local time T with the timestamp in the message T'.
我们合并时间戳的方法是
And the way we're going to merge those is
逐个位置合并两个向量时间戳
we're going to go through the two vectors element-wise.
我们先取出T中的第一个元素和T'中的第一个元素
And so, we're going to take the first element of T and the first element of T'.
我们取这两个元素的最大值 把最大值作为T的第一个元素
I'm going to take the maximum of those two, and that becomes the first element of T.
我们再取T中的第二个元素和T'中的第二个元素
We're going to take the second element of T, the second element of T',
再取最大值 以此类推
take the maximum, and so on.
我们逐个位置取出最大值 用最大值更新变量T
So, element-wise, we take the maximum, and the result is this updated variable T here.
接下来 我们增加T的本地计数器值 将消息m传递给应用
Then, again, we increment the local entry in T and we deliver m to the application.
我们通过一个具体的例子来演示向量时钟的执行流程
So, let's look at an example of what this actually looks like here.
我们把向量写为
So, I'm going to write my vectors as being
A是向量中的第一个元素
A is the first entry in the vector,
B是向量中的第二个元素
B is the second entry in the vector,
C是向量中的第三个元素
and C is the third entry.
当A发生了第一个本地事件时
And so, here, when the first local event happens at A,
这意味着A要增加向量中自己位置的计数值
that means A increments its own entry in the vector.
这意味着第一个元素变为1
So, that means the first entry becomes 1,
向量中剩余元素取值保持不变
and the remaining entries in the vector remain unchanged.
当A发生了第二个本地事件时 A再增加自己位置的计数值
On the second event here, again, A increments its own entry.
时间戳变为<2,0,0>
So, this becomes <2,0,0>.
向量<2,0,0>会被附加在消息m_1上 通过网络发送输出
And <2,0,0> is the vector that is attached to message m_1 as it sent over the network.
当B收到<2,0,0>时 B要逐个位置取最大值
Now, when <2,0,0> is received by B, it does the element-wise maximum.
这意味着B的时间戳变为了<2,0,0>
So, that means it also ends up with <2,0,0>.
随后 B增加自己位置的计数值
And then, it increments its own entry.
因为下一个事件是B执行的
Now, because this is B executing now,
因此B增加向量时间戳中自己位置的计数值
it increments the second entry of the vector clock.
这个事件的时间戳最终变为了<2,1,0>
And so, we end up with <2,1,0> as the timestamp of this particular event.
B下一个事件的时间戳为<2,1,0> 这同样涉及一次本地递增操作
On the next event by B, we have <2,2,0>, because, again, it's a local increment.
时间戳<2,2,0>会被附加在消息m_2上
<2,2,0> is the timestamp that gets attached to message m_2
通过网络发送出去
as it gets sent over the network.
当C收到消息时 C同样要逐个元素取最大值
And again, we have the element-wise maximum here when it gets received.
C在收到消息之前会执行一个事件
So, here, even though there was a previous event on C,
因为这是由C执行的事件 因此这一个事件的时间戳为<0,0,1>
that previous event will have had <0,0,1>, because it's executed on node C,
也就是C要增加向量第三个位置的计数值
which is incrementing the third entry of the vector,
但随后 C要逐个位置取最大值 并增加C对应位置的计数值
but then, here we do the element-wise maximum, and the increment of C's entry.
我们得到<2,2,2>
So, we get <2,2,2>.
我们可以这样理解这些向量
So, one way of thinking about these vectors here is that
每一个向量都表示一个事件集合
a vector represents a set of events.
我们以B第二个事件的<2,2,0>为例
And so, let's take for example this <2,2,0> here, the second event on B.
这个时间戳表示一个事件集合
This represents the set of events
事件集合定义为 此事件本身再加上所有之前发生的事件
which is this event itself plus all of the events that happened before it.
如果我们令其为事件e
So, if that's this event e,
则这个时间戳表示e和e之前发生的所有事件所构成的集合求并集
that's the set of e union all of the events that happened before e.
在示意图中 我们可以把时间戳看成
And so, visually, we can think of this in the diagram
按照时间顺序倒转
by traveling backwards in time
通过倒转到达所有之前发生的事件
and finding all of the events that we can reach through travelling backwards
倒转过程既覆盖每个节点独立执行的事件顺序
either on each node's individual execution order,
也覆盖接收方收到的每一条消息
or by going backwards from the receipt to each sending of messages.
这里的意思是 从<2,2,0>开始
And so, here, that means from <2,2,0>,
我们可以回到<2,1,0> 回到<2,0,0> 回到<1,0,0>
we can get back to <2,1,0>, we can get back to <2,0,0> and <1,0,0>.
我们可以从<2,2,0>倒转 到达这4个事件
So, we can reach these 4 events here by going backwards from <2,2,0>.
我们可以到达A的前两个事件 到达B的前两个事件
We can reach the first two events on A, and we can reach the first two events on B,
但我们无法从此事件倒转到C的事件
but none of the events on C by going backwards from this event.
这就是此事件对应<2,2,0>的原因
And that's why it has <2,2,0>.
意思是此时间戳包含A的前两个事件、B的前两个事件 不包含C的事件
It means the first two events on A, the first two events on B, and no events from C.
时间戳包含了事件之间的关联性
So, here you can see this correspondence.
时间戳和系统中的事件集合
There's a direct correspondence
有直接的对应关系
between these vectors and the set of events in the system.
向量时间戳
The vector is essentially a way of
总结了系统中已发生的全部事件
summarizing a set of events that occurred in the system
时间戳记录了每个节点
simply by counting for each node
从开始到现在
from the start of that node's execution of how many events
历史上所发生的全部事件
down do we go in that node's history.
现在 我们定义了这些向量
So now, now that we've defined these vectors
并定义了计算向量的算法
and the algorithm for computing the vectors,
我们现在可以比较各个向量了
we can now compare them.
首先 我们定义相等性
And so, first of all, we're going to say that
如果每个元素都相等 则这两个向量时间戳也相等
two vector timestamps are equal if each of the elements are equal.
如果对于每一个位置i都有T[i]=T'[i] 则T=T'
So, T=T' if for each of the elements i, T[i]=T'[i].
相等性的定义非常直接
And so, this is just a straightforward equality.
类似地 我们定义≤运算符
Also, similarly, we define the ≤ operator.
如果我们对比两个向量
So, T≤T' if we compare the two vectors,
查看T和T'的第一个元素 满足T[1]≤T'[1]
look at the first element of T and the first element of T', and if that's less than or equal,
第二个元素满足T[2]≤T'[2] 第三个元素满足T[3]≤T'[3]
and the second one is less than or equal, and the third one is less than or equal,
如果所有位置都满足T[i]≤T'[i]
if all of them are less than or equal,
则我们称T≤T'
then we say that that T≤T'.
我们可以把严格小于（T<T'）定义为T≤T'且T≠T'
We can define <, strictly less than simply as being T≤T', and then T≠T',
意思是向量中至少有一个元素不相等
which means that there must be at least one element in which they differ,
但其他所有位置的元素都满足小于等于关系
but they might be the same in all of the other elements.
最后 给定两个向量时间戳T和T'
And finally, it is possible that for two vector timestamps T and T',
既不满足T≤T' 也不满足T'≤T
neither is T≤T' nor is T'≤T,
此时 我们称T和T'是不可比较的
and in that case, we say that T and T' are incomparable.
现在 大家可以把此结论和我之前讲的“时间戳表示事件集合”联系到一起
And now, here you can relate back to what I just said about sets of events.
我前面讲到 V(a)相当于
So, remember, we said that here, this V(a) here corresponds to
事件a加上a之前发生的所有事件所构成的集合
the set of event a plus all of the events that happened before a.
V(b)相当于
And the V(b) corresponds to
事件b加上b之前发生的所有事件所构成的集合
the set of event b plus all of the events that happened before b.
向量的≤关系等价于
And now, this ≤ relationship on the vectors corresponds exactly to
两个事件集合满足子集关系
a subset relationship on those two sets of events.
这个结论很有意思
This is quite interesting now.
这个结论很好地体现了向量时间戳的含义
This gives you a nice way of reasoning about what these vectors actually mean,
因为向量时间戳相当于事件集合
because since they correspond to sets of events,
因此向量时间戳的≤关系描述了事件集合的子集关系
there's a subset relationship between the two.
一个事件集合可能是另一个事件集合的子集
And it might be the case that one is a subset of the other,
一个事件集合也可能不是另一个事件集合的子集
or it might be the case that neither is a subset of the other,
因为两个事件集合中可能存在非共有事件
because there are some elements that they don't have in common.
向量时间戳的顺序定义非常有用
And so, now, this order that we have defined on these vector timestamps is very useful,
因为向量时间戳的顺序定义严格描述了此前发生关系
because it corresponds exactly to the happens-before relationship.
向量时间戳顺序是一个偏序
So, it gives us a partial order.
此偏序与因果关系保持一致
And this partial order is consistent with causality.
首先 我们可以得出结论 给定两个事件a和b
So, first of all, we have the fact that given two events a and b,
根据顺序定义 V(a)<V(b)当且仅当a→b
V(a)<V(b) according to this order above here if and only if a→b.
在Lamport时间戳中 我们只有单向蕴含关系
So, for the Lamport timestamps, we only had a one-way implication.
也就是说 如果a→b 则一个时间戳小于另一个时间戳
We had that if a→b, then one timestamp is less than the other.
但在向量时间戳中 我们得到了当且仅当关系
But with vector clocks, we have an if-and-only-if relationship.
这是一个双向蕴含关系
It's a bi-directional implication.
给定两个时间戳 我们可以得出结论
So, we can also conclude that looking at two timestamps,
如果一个时间戳小于另一个时间戳 那么一定有a→b
if one is less than the other, then we know that a→b.
时间戳也唯一标识了事件
It's also the case that the timestamps uniquely identify events.
如果两个事件拥有相同的向量时间戳
So, if two events have the same vector timestamps,
则这些事件都是相同的事件
that means that those events are the same.
这也是一个双向蕴含关系 是一个当且仅当关系
And so, this is again a bi-directional implication. it's an if-and-only-if.
最后 如果按照上述定义 两个时间戳不可比较
And finally, if the two timestamps are incomparable according to the definition up here,
这意味着两个事件是并发的
that means that the two events are concurrent.
如果两个事件是并发的 则它们的时间戳也不可比较
And if the two events are concurrent, then their timestamps will be incomparable.
通过使用向量时钟
So, what we now have here using vector clocks
我们得到了一种计算此前发生关系的方法
is a way of computing the happens-before relationship.
在这之间 此前发生关系只是一个抽象的定义
So far, the happens-before relation has been essentially this abstract definition.
我们可以通过查看事件示意图
By looking at the diagram of the events on paper,
指出哪些事件在其他事件之前发生
we can work out what thing happened before which other thing,
但这不是一种算法描述
but that's not an algorithm for computing it,
有了向量时钟后
whereas here with vector clocks,
我们得到了一个算法
we actually have an algorithm
应用此算法可以严格计算出哪些事件在其他事件之前发生
for computing exactly which event happened before which other event.
我们也能计算出两个事件是否是并发的
And we have a way of telling whether two events are concurrent or not.
这就是与Lamport时钟相比
So, this is the really interesting thing about vector clocks
向量时钟所满足的有趣性质
that Lamport clocks do not have.
这就是本小节
So, these have been
我们要学习的两种逻辑时钟
the two types of logical time that we're going to look at in this section.